Guide to the Abbie G. Sanderson Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Abbie G. Sanderson Papers
1907-1961
RG 149
Yale University Divinity School Library
4
(10 boxes)
Detailed family correspondence, writings, and collected material document the life and work of a single woman missionary in South China. Abbie G. Sanderson was an American Baptist missionary in South China from 1918 to 1937 and 1946 to 1953. She later taught at a girls' school in Sendai, Japan, and retired in 1959.
Sanderson, Abbie G.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Abbie Sanderson.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
Abbie G. Sanderson was born in Greenville, New Hampshire on May 27, 1893. She graduated from Coburn Classical Institute and Colby College, Waterville, Maine. After teaching in Maine for two years, she sailed to Swatow in 1918. She served the South China Baptist Mission (American Baptist) in the Swatow area from 1918 to 1937 and 1946 to 1953, teaching at the Abigail Hart Scott Memorial School, also known as Kak Chieh Girls' School.
Primarily based in Swatow, Sanderson spent some summer months in cooler areas such as Kuliang, Fukien. She was on furlough in the U.S. during 1924, returning to China in December of that year. From May to October 1927 she was stationed in the Philippines due to disruptions in the Swatow area. Sanderson was on furlough in the U.S. in 1931, returning to Swatow in February of 1932. She extended her furlough in 1937 due to her father's health, and then was prevented by the war from returning to China until 1946. Sanderson was held in solitary confinement for twenty-one months prior to her release from Communist China in 1953. She taught at a girls' school in Sendai, Japan from 1954 until her retirement in 1959.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of this collection is Sanderson's detailed, regular letters to her family in the U.S. This record group complements the papers of other Baptist missionaries to South China held by YDSL, including those of the Campbell family, Hartwell family, Ellison and Lottie Hildreth.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Writings, Diaries, Notes
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia
IV. Collected Material
V. Photographs
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection have been digitized. See: http://divinity-adhoc.library.yale.edu/AbbieSandersonPapers/
Missions -- China; Women missionaries; Sanderson, Abbie G.
- Correspondence, 1907-1953; Series I
  Existence and Location of Copies
  Much of the correspondence has been digitized. See: http://divinity-adhoc.library.yale.edu/AbbieSandersonPapers/
  - Family correspondence
    - Abbie G. Sanderson (AGS) to mother and father, 1907-1918 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - AGS to family, enroute to China and arrival in Swatow, 1918 Mar 14 - Apr 29 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - AGS to family from Swatow and Thai Iong ("up in the hills"), 1918 May 7 - Aug 28 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - AGS to family, from Thai Iong and Swatow, 1918 Sep-Dec (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, 1919 Jan - Apr (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow and Thai Iong, 1919 May - Aug (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - AGS to family, from Thai Iong and Swatow, and from extended trip into countryside (81 page journal/letter begins from "The Gospel" houseboat on the River Hang), 1919 Sep - Dec (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - AGS to family, from boat on trip to countryside, from Swatow, from Chaoyang, 1919 Jan - Apr (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow and Kuliang, out Foochow [Fuzhou], Fukien [Fujian], 1920 May 2- Nov 8 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, 1921 Jan - Jun (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, 1921 Jul - Dec (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, Chaochowfu, Canton, 1922 Jan - Apr (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, Chaoyang, 1922 May - Aug (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, Chaoyang, 1922 Sep - Dec (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, 1923 Jan - Jun (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - AGS to family, on furlough in U.S., en route back to China, arrival back in Swatow, 1924 Feb - Dec (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, 1925 Jan - Apr (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, Shanghai, 1925 May - Aug (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - AGS to family, from Shanghai, Amoy, Swatow, 1925 Sep - Dec (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, Chaochowfu, 1926 Jan - Apr (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, Hong Kong, Peitaiho, 1926 May - Aug (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, 1926 Sep - Dec (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - AGS to family, from Chaochowfu, Swatow, Chaoyang, Shanghai, 197 Jan - Apr (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow and Philippine Islands, where she was stationed due to disruptions in China, 1927 May - Aug (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - AGS to family, from Philippine Islands, returning to Swatow in October, 1927 Sep - Dec (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, with some enclosed letters to/from others, 1928 Jan - Apr (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, with some enclosed letters to/from others, 1928 May - Aug (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, 1928 Sep-Dec (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, 1929 Jan - Apr (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow and while on vacation from Philippine Islands, 1929 May - Aug (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, 1929 Sep - Dec (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, 1930 Jan - Mar (Box 4, Folder 32a)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, Chaochowfu, 1930 Apr- Jun (Box 4, Folder 32b)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow following return from furlough in U.S., 1932 Jan - Jun (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, from Hong Kong and Philippine Islands during vacation, 1932 Jul - Dec (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - AGS to familiy, from Swatow, 1933 Jan - Apr (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow and Kuliang, 1933 May - Aug (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, incl. enclosed letter to mission board in NY, 1933 Sep - Dec (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, 1934 Jan - Apr (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, Shanghai, Double Island (Swatow), including enclosed poems by Chinese students, 1934 May - Aug (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, 1934 Sep - Dec (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, Shanghai, 1935 Jan - Apr (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow and Kuliang [Fuzhou], with enclosed poems by Chinese students and enclosed missionary circulars from others, 1935 May - Aug (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, with enclosed excerpts of article by Toyohiko Kagawa and circular letters from other missionaries, 1935 Sep - Dec (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, with enclosed letter from AGS to Mrs. Humphreys, Baptist Foreign Mission Society, 1936 Jan - Apr (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, with enclosed letter from AGS to Mrs. Humphreys, Baptist Foreign Mission Society, 1936 May - Aug (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, Hong Kong, 1936 Sep - Dec (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - AGS to family, from Swatow, 1937 Jan - May (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - AGS to brother Arthur, from Swatow, Hong Kong, and ship, re. period "supervision by the People's Government" in Swatow, awaiting exit permit, exit to Hong Kong in early 1953, 1950 - 1953 (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - AGS to family, undated letters, fragments, and misfiled letters from 1920, 1922, 1920, 1922, no date (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - General correspondence
    - Circular and general letters of AGS, 1918-1949 (Box 7, Folder 50)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes general letters to friends and to the churches that supported her.
    - AGS to/from representatives of Woman's American Baptist Foreign Mission Society in New York, 1926-1937 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - AGS to Mary Clough, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 52)
    - AGS to Mary Clough, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - AGS to Mary Clough, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - AGS to Mary Clough, 1949-1953 (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - AGS to Idella K. Fairman, 1918-1935, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - AGS to/from Shanghai College, Herman C. E. Liu, President, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - AGS to/from other friends, colleagues, and students, A- L, 1919-1965 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - AGS to/from other friends, colleagues, and students, M - W, 1921-1949 (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - Letters of others, including circular letters from Baptist missionaries such as Velva Brown, Elsie Kittlitz, Marion Stephens, 1918-1951, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 60)
- Writings, Diaries, Notes, 1919-1961, n.d; Series II
  Much of this series has been digitized. See: http://divinity-adhoc.library.yale.edu/AbbieSandersonPapers/
  - "Diary and Daily Reminder" (bound volume with notes and diary entries, 1935); "Five Year Diary" (with brief entries for 1936), 1935, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - Typescript writings of AGS, incl.: ""Description of a Trip on a Houseboat" (1919); "Laying the Corner Stone of the Jubilee Building, Swatow, China"; "The Appeal of the Present Situation in Young People's Work", 1919-1925, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Issue of "The New East" periodical including article by AGS: "The Kak Chieh Girls' School" (1921); fragments of writings, 1921, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 63)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1924-1961, n.d.; Series III
  - Biographical documentation of AGS, including passport, brochure, Colby College information form, newspaper clippings, 1924-1961, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 64)
  - Dress designs, lists of names and household items, financial documents, 1937-1938, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 65)
- Collected Material, 1925-1951, n.d.; Series IV
  - Documentation re. the Abigail Hart Scott Memorial School, Swatow, and other Baptist mission work in South China, 1925-1935, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 66)
  - Tracts, pamphlets re. China, Japan, and Philippines, incl. "Woman in China" by Adele M. Fielde, "New Life from Within" by Madame Chiang Kai-shek; other miscellaneous typescript writings, 1932-1940, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 67)
  - Newspaper clippings regarding missionaries in China under Communists, 1948-1951 (Box 8, Folder 68)
  - Chinese language material incl. two hymnals, tract titled "Be a Fiery Christian", words to hymns in Swatow Chinese, music sheets for quartet, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 69)
- Photographs, ca.1918-1950; Series V
  Many of the photographs have been digitized. Search for Sanderson at http://web.library.yale.edu/digital-collections/divinity-library-photographs
  - Portraits of Abbie G. Sanderson, ca.1918-1950 (Box 9, Folder 70)
  - Sanderson with friends and colleagues, ca.1918-1950 (Box 9, Folder 71)
  - Sanderson with friends and colleagues, ca.1918-1950 (Box 9, Folder 72)
  - Sanderson with friends and colleagues, ca.1918-1950,n.d. (Box 9, Folder 72)
  - Groups of colleagues and friends, including Swatow mission conferences, ca.1918-1950 (Box 9, Folder 74)
  - Groups of colleagues and friends, including Swatow mission conferences, ca.1918-1950,n.d. (Box 9, Folder 75)
  - Students, ca.1918-1950 (Box 9, Folder 76)
  - Chinese families and everyday life, ca.1918-1950 (Box 9, Folder 77)
  - Buildings, including mission compound damage after typhoon and earthquake damage in Kak Chieh, ca.1918-1950 (Box 9, Folder 78)
  - Scenery, ca.1918-1950 (Box 9, Folder 79)
  - Scenery, ca.1918-1950 (Box 9, Folder 80)
  - Large group photos - faculty, missionaries, ca.1918-1950 (Box 9, Folder 81)
  - Large group photos - students, athletic teams, ca.1918-1950 (Box 9, Folder 82)
  - Large photos - buildings, scenery, ca.1918-1950 (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - Duplicate and unidentified photographs, ca.1918-1950 (Box 10)
  - Oversize photographs, 1920-1937 (Box OV-d1)
    Five photographs, including Girls' School, Swatow (1925), faculty of Kak Kuang Academy (1937)